A Guide to the Roberta Wellford Collection of Women's Rights Ephemera, 1915-1956
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
The Roberta Wellford Collection of Women's Rights Ephemera 1915-1956
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 86
53 items
Roberta Wellford
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Wellford collection was donated by the Rare Book Department at the University of Virginia to Cabell Library Special Collections and Archives on 16 August 1976.
Biographical/Historical Information
Roberta Wellford was a charter member, secretary, and director of the Equal Suffrage League of Virginia and worked to push the organization of the Virginia League of Women Voters (VLWV) in the 1920s. She participated in the World War I war effort as a volunteer with the YMCA for troops in Paris and in Germany. As a member of the VLWV, she actively promoted public education in Virginia and supported the League of Nations and the World Court. Wellford was a member of the Daughters of the Confederacy, the Woman's Club, and the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals. She was active in the preservation of Virginia antiquities, the Virginia Museum of Fine Art, the Virginia Historical Society, and the Valentine Museum.
Wellford was born in Greenville, South Carolina in 1873 to Major Philip Alexander Wellford C.S.A. and Belle Street Wellford. She died on December 28, 1956 in Richmond, Virginia and is buried in Hollywood Cemetery. (Richmond Times Dispatch, 29 December 1956; Richmond News Leader, 28 December 1956)
Scope and Content Information
This collection compiled by Roberta Wellford consists of 53 items of women's suffrage and civil rights ephemera from the early 20th century. Included in this assortment are two copies of an address by Carrie Chapman Catt before the League of Women Voters (1920), National League of Women Voters (NLWV) pamphlets, booklets, and notes from the 1921, 1922, 1923 conventions and four copies of organization by-laws (undated); NLWV booklets: "A Record of Four Years...1920-1924"; two copies of a booklet entitled "The Eight-Hour Day for Women" (1915), and one organization bulletin (1918) from the National Women's Trade Union League.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Boston League of Women Voters, 1921 (Box-folder 1:1)
  A flyer and a play program
- League of Women Voters, 1920 (Box-folder 1:2)
  Address by Carrie Chapman Catt and a pamphlet
- Maryland League of Women Voters, 1922 (Box-folder 1:3)
  Menu
- Massachusetts League of Women Voters, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
  Pamphlet on education
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box-folder 1:5)
  3 items
- National League of Women Voters, undated, 1920-1924 (Box-folder 1:6)
  25 items
- National League of Women Voters, A Record of Four Years...1920-1924, 1924 (Box-folder 1:7)
  Booklet
- National League of Women Voters, Lessons for the Study of Citizenship, undated (Box-folder 1:8)
- National League of Women Voters, Convention, 1921 (Box-folder 1:9)
  Notes
- National Women's Trade Union League, undated, 1915, 1917, 1918 (Box-folder 1:10)
  10 items
- News Clippings, undated (Box-folder 1:11)
  2 items
- New York State League of Women Voters, The Next War, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
  Pamphlet